Register of the Herbert S. Klein collection
Hoover Institution Archives
Herbert S. Klein collection
1760-1991
2012C50
Hoover Institution Archives
5 manuscript boxes (2 linear feet)
The collection is comprised of printed matter and research materials relating to the history and modern politics of Bolivia. The printed matter consists of pamphlets, monographs, and serial issues that largely pertain to Bolivian leftist authors and organizations. The research materials and notes concern land use and property issues in Bolivia during the 18th and 19th centuries. These materials were used as the basis of Herbert S. Klein's work, Haciendas and Ayllus: Rural Society in the Bolivian Andes in the 18th and 19th Centuries (1993).
Klein, Herbert S.
Access
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2012.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection is comprised of printed matter and research materials relating to the history and modern politics of Bolivia. The printed matter consists of pamphlets, monographs, and serial issues that largely pertain to Bolivian leftist authors and organizations. The research materials and notes concern land use and property issues in Bolivia during the 18th and 19th centuries. These materials were used as the basis of Herbert S. Klein's work, Haciendas and Ayllus: Rural Society in the Bolivian Andes in the 18th and 19th Centuries (1993).
Arrangement Statement
The collection is organized into 2 series: Pamphlets, monographs, and serial issues; and Research materials and notes
Biographical/Historical note
1936 Born, Chicago
1957 Receives B.A., University of Chicago
1963 Awarded Ph.D., University of Chicago
1967 Slavery in the Americas: A Comparative Study of Virginia and Cuba
1969 Parties and Political Change in Bolivia, 1880-1952
1978 The Middle Passage: Comparative Studies in the Atlantic Slave Trade
1982 Bolivia, the Evolution of a Multi-Ethnic Society
1986 African Slavery in Latin America and the Caribbean
1993 Haciendas and Ayllus: Rural Society in the Bolivian Andes in the 18th and 19th Centuries
1999 The Atlantic Slave Trade
2003 A Concise History of Bolivia
Bolivia--Politics and government.
- Pamphlets, monographs, and serial issues, 1916-1971 (Box 1-3)
  - Asi lucharon...los hombres del M.N.R., undated (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Lavalle, A., Fines y medias de la revolución democrático-burguesa, undated (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Antezana E., Luis, La lucha entre Cliza y Ucareña, undated (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Manifiesto y programa minimo de la "Unión Nacional", undated (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Movimiento Nacionalista Revolucionario, undated (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Anaya, Ricardo, Unidos Venceremos, undated (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Camacho, Eliodoro, La política liberal, 1916 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Bustamante, Daniel S., Programa político, 1918 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Primera convención del Partido Nacionalista, 1928 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - Programa Republicano Socialista, 1930 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Congreso Nacional de Acción Social Católica, 1931 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Recurso generales con que han contado las administraciones en las gestiones..., 1932 (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - Sartor resartor, 1933 (Box-folder 1: 13)
  - Bajo el régimen militar socialista..., 1936 (Box-folder 1: 14)
  - Informe presentado por el Señor Coronel Presidente..., 1937 (Box-folder 1: 15)
  - Programa político de la Associación Nacional de Ex-Combatientes Socialistas, 1937 (Box-folder 1: 16)
  - La Obra de la Junta Militar Socialista en el Gobierno, 1937 (Box-folder 1: 17)
  - Canelas, Demetrio, Documentos políticos, 1938 (Box-folder 1: 18)
  - Marof, Tristan, La verdad socialista en Bolivia, 1938 (Box-folder 1: 19)
  - ¡Hacia la unidad de las izquierdas Bolivianas!, 1939 (Box-folder 1: 20)
  - Marof, Tristan, La emancipación económica de Bolivia, 1940 (Box-folder 1: 21)
  - Marof, Tristan, El peligro nazi en Bolivia, 1941 (Box-folder 1: 22)
  - Programa y estatutos del Partido de Izquierda Revolucionaria, 1941 (Box-folder 1: 23)
  - Victor Paz Estenssoro y la masacre de Catavi, 1943 (Box-folder 1: 24)
  - Bolivia bajo terrorismo nazifascista, 1944 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Estatutos, reglamento general y ritual, 1944 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - La política Liberal, 1944 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - Lora, Guillermo, Definición, 1947 (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - Anaya, Ricardo, Imperialismo, rosca y miseria, 1947 (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - Tamayo rinde cuenta, 1947 (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - Masacre de Potosi, 1948 (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - Lora, Guillermo, Defensa de la Tesis de Pulacayo, 1948 (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - Conclusiones del VIII pleno del P.I.R., 1950 (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - Diez de Medina, Fernando, Siripaka, la batalla de Bolivia, 1950 (Box-folder 2: 10)
  - Iñiguez, Juan and Antonio Llosa, Antitesis de Pulacayo, 1950 (Box-folder 2: 11)
  - Nacionalismo Boliviano, 1952 (Box-folder 2: 12)
  - Valencia Vega, Alipio, Desarrollo del pensamiento político en Bolivia, 1953 (Box-folder 2: 13)
  - Montenegro, Carlos, Documentos, 1954 (Box-folder 2: 14)
  - Programa ideológico y estatutos de la Central Obrera Boliviana, 1954 (Box-folder 2: 15)
  - Montenegro, Carlos, Culpables, 1955 (Box-folder 2: 16)
  - Sánchez, Primitivo, El Partido Liberal en el gobierno y la oposición, 1955 (Box-folder 2: 17)
  - Revolución, numero 1, 1956 (Box-folder 2: 18)
  - Zorrilla, Jose Gamarra, Apuntes sobre posición y doctrina de Falange Socialista Boliviana, 1956 (Box-folder 2: 19)
  - Primero congreso nacional del P.C.B., 1959 (Box-folder 2: 20)
  - Programa obrero, 1959 (Box-folder 2: 21)
  - ¿Que es y que quiere el por?, 1959 (Box-folder 2: 22)
  - Sindicatos y revolución, 1960 (Box-folder 2: 23)
  - Peticiones del Episcopado de Bolivia respecto a la reforma de la constitución, 1961 (Box-folder 2: 24)
  - P.I.R. y desarrollo nacional, 1961 (Box-folder 2: 25)
  - Debray, Régis, Defensa en Camiri, 1968 (Box-folder 2: 26)
  - Lora, Guillermo, Bolivia y la revolución permanente, 1968 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - Arias, David, La masacre de San Juan, 1969 (Box-folder 3: 2)
  - Masas, 1969-1971
    - June-October 1969 (Box-folder 3: 3)
    - January-November 1970 (Box-folder 3: 4)
    - January-April 1971 (Box-folder 3: 5)
- Research materials and notes, 1760-1991 (Box 3-5)
  - Pacajes, 1767-1883 (Box-folder 3: 6)
  - Yungas, 1882 (Box-folder 3: 7)
  - Sicasica, 1887-1897 (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - Omasuyos, 1900 (Box-folder 3: 9)
  - Muñecas cadastro, 1881 (Box-folder 3: 10)
  - Cercado, 1888 (Box-folder 3: 11)
  - Chulumani, 1882 (Box-folder 3: 12)
  - Inquisivi, 1881 (Box-folder 3: 13)
  - Larecaja, 1881 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - Leading Yungas hacendados, 1785-1991 (Box-folder 4: 2)
  - Los Yungas (Chulumani), 1982-1991 (Box-folder 4: 3)
  - Diez de Medina, Francisco Tadeo, 1792-1982 (Box-folder 4: 4)
  - Viedma y Narváez, Francisco, 1978 (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - Padrones, 1852-1982 (Box-folder 4: 6)
  - Archivo Nacional de Bolivia, sections of "Tierras e indios" and "Expedientes coloniales", 1782-1982 (Box-folder 4: 7)
  - Indian tribute censuses, 1773-1991 (Box-folder 5: 1)
  - Caupolicán, 1881 (Box-folder 5: 2)
  - Carangas-La Plata, 1982 (Box-folder 5: 3)
  - Cochabamba-padrones de indios, 1982 (Box-folder 5: 4)
  - Master list of padrones, 1991 (Box-folder 5: 5)
  - Director General de Contribuciones (report on new cadastral taxes), 1881-1884 (Box-folder 5: 6)
  - Miscellaneous censuses (Alto Peru), 1760-1982 (Box-folder 5: 7)
  - Testamento de Joaquín de Trucios, 1771-1982 (Box-folder 5: 8)
  - La Paz province-government structure, 1792-1982 (Box-folder 5: 9)
  - Caja reál de Potosí, 1750-1982 (Box-folder 5: 10)
  - Omasuyos, 1990 (Box-folder 5: 11)
  - Omasuyos-inscripciones de propriedades rústicas, 1882 (Box-folder 5: 12)
  - Paredes, M. Rigoberto, La Provincia de Omasuyu, 1955 (Box-folder 5: 13)
  - Libros de parroquia, 1877-1991 (Box-folder 5: 14)
  - Archivo particular de Soux Muñoz, 1792 (Box-folder 5: 15)
  - La Paz, 1894 (Box-folder 5: 16)
  - Sicasica (Cadastral), 1881 (Box-folder 5: 17)
  - Pueblo codebook, 1991 (Box-folder 5: 18)